So today's דף Daf is מ Mem 40, and we begin at
the very bottom of לט עמוד ב, Lamed Tet Amud Bet, and
we had moved on from מצה Matzah and מרור Maror to discussing
back to חמץ Chametz concerns and taking bran and putting it in
water in order to feed the chickens and various issues that concerns
about becoming חמץ, Chametz, and the גמרא Gemara stated very important that
once you've baked or roasted or even scalded the grain, it can
no longer become חמץ. Chametz. And at the same time the גמרא
Gemara ended with what is against the concern of געבראכטס, Gebrochts, but
of course then the גמרא Gemara ended by saying that in the
case of a certain type of a roasted grain and to add
it to the as a thickener for the soup, you shouldn't do
it because maybe it didn't get roasted well enough and then it
will become חמץ, Chametz, and that exactly is the concern of געבראכטס.
Gebrochts. I mean, they go, געבראכטס Gebrochts goes so far as talking
even about baked מצות, Matzos, but the issue that maybe we didn't
do 100 percent and maybe there is still some concern. So that's
a sort of theme that the גמרא Gemara continues with now starting
at the very beginning of לט עמוד ב. Lamed Tet Amud Bet.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, five lines before the end of
the דף, Daf, five words, excuse me, very last line. אמר רב
יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, לא לחלוט איניש,
Lo lichlot inish, people should not scald, again, pouring, you know, putting
it in boiling hot water is considered to cook it without it
giving a chance to become חמץ. Chametz. As I mentioned yesterday, the
שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says like nowadays we can't trust anybody, nobody
knows how to do חליטה Chalitah correctly, we can't trust anybody to
do it correct, so we cannot at all rely on חליטה Chalitah
as a way of avoiding חמץ. Chametz. And it's אסור assur to
if you did חליטה, Chalitah, it's still אסור, assur, you have to
assume that it became חמץ. Chametz. I will say interestingly that the
I think it's the חיי אדם Chai Adam says, one of the
late אחרונים Achronim says that apparently dealing with scenarios where sometimes Jews
had to prepare food for quartered troops over פסח, Pesach, I
mean I assume during the year but also over פסח, Pesach, and
had to prepare various grain products, and in those circumstances he recommends
to do it by scalding. So even though of course חס ושלום
chas v'shalom we would never like allow it during the year, we
can't trust this or rely on this and so on, there's you
know you're getting grain and flour in contact with water you have
to be concerned about חמץ Chametz even though according to the גמרא,
Gemara, you know the גמרא Gemara felt that it was possible although
now we'll see the concerns in a minute, but when there was
no other choice and you know you had the king's troops coming
to visit the town, you had very few options, so then he
says that that would be a time to rely on this. Yes.
Do you have anything to say about this kind of logic, in
other words,
חליטה שלהם לא כחליטה שלנו Chalitah shelahem lo k'chalitah shelanu or הדיחות
שלנו לא כדיחות
שלהם?
hadihut shelanu lo k'dihut
shelahem?
So I think sometimes you do find that and sometimes it genuinely
has to do with, like, you know, not knowing exactly what was
referred to, etc. Here how much חכמה chochma does it take to
make sure, I mean you could say make sure it's boiling hot,
make sure whatever, I think it's much more just the concern of
חמץ. Chametz. I mean it's one thing to say if you baked
it
dry we're not going to be concerned then that there's going to
be a new problem, but to take unbaked wheat, put it in
water, so I don't know, I think that the sense I get
is that it's not coming from a genuine concern of lack of
expertise, it's coming from this great sensitivity or great חומרות chumras around
חמץ. Chametz.
But they did it in the earlier generations, they did it, so
in a way is it a way of saying with some הלכה
halachic authority we're just not comfortable in the same way?
Yes, I think that that is correct, meaning is that true all
the time or is that sometimes a factor? I think often there
is a reality of not knowing exactly what's being referred to. Here
my sense is it's exactly what you said, that it's a way
of saying we're not comfortable with this anymore and we're just going
to assume we can't do what the גמרא, Gemara, you know, we
don't know well enough how to do it. Okay, but not that
that's the real issue, the real issue is we're not comfortable. I
would agree that that's the issue here. So anyway, regarding sort of
ongoing concerns, so let's read that again. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, לא לחלוט איניש, lo lichlot inish, a person should not scald,
you know, the wheat. תרי חטי, Trei chittei,
now you're going to see where some of these concerns might emerge
from, two pieces of wheat, two kernels of wheat, בהדי הדדי, bahadi
hadadi, together at the same time. Why? דילמא אזלא חדא ויתבא בציריא
דחברתה, De'ilma azla chada v'yatva b'tzira'ei d'chaverta,
one will go and it'll lodge itself in the crack of the
other kernel of wheat, ולא סליק להו דיקולא דמיא, v'lo salik lehu
dikula d'maya,
and the stream of water won't get between, won't get to the
other one. So basically what will prevent it from becoming חמץ Chametz
is that it all hit boiling hot water, but maybe two kernels
of wheat will be right on top of one another and there'll
be a section of a kernel that won't get to boiling hot
water. So yeah exactly. Basically a type of a חציצה. chatzitza. But
now if when you're doing this, you have to make sure that
every kernel is separate from every other kernel, you can understand, you
know, where these types of concerns come from and why we don't
want to continue to be doing this. מארבע רוחתא m'arba ruchata from
the four, all four directions, actually six, but okay, you know, six
sides. Anyway, I don't know, it depends how it's shaped. ואתי לידי
חימוץ v'ati lidei chimutz and then it will be able to ferment.
ואמר אביי v'amar Abaye and Abaye also says, לא ליחרך איניש תרי
שיבולי בהדי הדדי lo lachrich inish t'rei shibolei bahadi hadadi you should
not, now even without water here, you should not roast two ears
of grain, I
mean you say ears even when it's not corn, like ears, what
do you say by wheat? Ears, what do you refer to? Sheaves?
No, isn't a sheaf when you take an entire thing and bind
it together?
I think it's like a stalk, it's the whole thing and it's
one little one. Okay, so I think a sheaf is the individual.
Oh it is?
But also tied together.
All right, anyway, I'm going to say okay, I'm going to say
ears. Anyway, okay, you should not, you should not go ahead and
roast two ears of wheat בהדי הדדי bahadi hadadi next to one
another. Right, שיבולי. shibolei. Right, okay, so fine, but the focus here
is on the, is on the place where the actual kernels are.
Anyway, you should not roast them next to one another. This is
without water. דילמא נפיק מיא מהאי ובא
לאידך dilma nafik maya mehai u'ba l'idach maybe there'll be water runoff
from one because they have a water content to them. So as
they're roasting, there'll be a water runoff and it'll go into the
other one. Okay, and then that'll be, it'll become חמץ. chametz. ואתי
לידי חימוץ v'ati lidei chimutz and it might come to חמץ chametz
to ferment. אמר ליה רבא amar leh Rava so Rava said, אי
הכי אפילו חדא נמי ei hachi afilu chada nami so then you
shouldn't be able to even roast one stalk. Why? דילמא נפיק מהאי
רישא ובא לאידך רישא dilma nafik mehai reisha u'ba l'idach reisha because
the water will runoff from the top of the stalk and be
absorbed by the other head or the bottom
of the ear. Shouldn't be able to make
מצה? matzah? Well not enough. No, because by the time it's flour,
I think you, I don't think that there's, is there water runoff
when you bake?
They're talking about the kernels.
They're talking about the kernels of wheat. Right, so the kernels of
wheat have a water content and when you roast them there'll be
water runoff.
What's the difference between adding water to it later and making it
into מצה? matzah? There's still water in there.
I think that there's just some things when you bake bread you
don't see a water runoff. When you bake, if you bake an
apple, right, you'll see a water runoff. So I just think it's
a question about the reality of there being a water runoff. Okay.
So he says, so that's what he says. And then, and he
says if that's true, you shouldn't even be able to do one
head of wheat.
Why are you roasting it if it's just going to evaporate?
I guess it's a question about how hot it is around it.
I mean, I don't know, you roast chicken and there's gravy at
the bottom, right? I mean, so it depends how much water, how
much whatever, but his point is maybe that's his point, like I
said, you know, if you're going to be concerned about that, then
you can't even do, you know, two kernels together, you know, or
one head at one time. All right, so let's see. אלא אמר
רבא ela amar Rava so Rava said, not what Michael is saying
that it all evaporates, but Rava said, מי פירות נינהו, mei peirot
ninhu, who cares if there's water runoff? It's water that's coming from
kernels of wheat, ומי פירות אינן מחמיצין u'mei peirot einan machmitzin and
מי פירות mei peirot don't become חמץ. chametz. Or now, that is,
now as we said, there's, you know, there's some גמרא Gemara that
indicate it does become חמץ, chametz, you know, maybe not full חמץ
chametz etc. But as I told you, the overwhelming consensus of the
ראשונים Rishonim and the פוסקים Poskim is, is that as long as
there's no additional water added, it doesn't become חמץ chametz at all.
So therefore, according, reading it through that lens, Rava is saying, if
all you have here is water coming from the wheat kernels themselves,
then it won't become חמץ chametz at all and it's not a
problem. Now, the issue here is, so that seems like a pretty
good argument. What did אביי Abaye feel? So it could be that
the question, interesting question is, what constitutes מי פירות? mei peirot? Because
this is, you know, where is the water content of a wheat
kernel coming from? I assume that it's absorbed water from rain and,
you know, from elsewhere. So it's not like, you know, it's a
little bit different than orange juice, which does have its, true every
juice or whatever does have a percentage of it which is water,
but fundamentally it's something different than water. This is, this is H2O
that was absorbed and is coming out. Okay, so does that give
it the status of מי פירות? mei peirot? That's at least my
understanding of the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. Somebody who
knows better the, the actual physical reality here could, is welcome to
correct me on that. But that's my understanding about why אביי Abaye
might not like this answer. Okay, so let's see what it says.
והדר ביה אביי v'hadar beh Abaye so the גמרא Gemara says and
Abaye reversed himself from his position. He said you're right, it's okay.
Why? Not because of what רבא Rava says, he still doesn't believe
this is called מי פירות. mei peirot. But for the following reason,
דכל אגב מדלייהו d'chol agav madleihu
as long as something is still sort of flowing, as long as
the water's just dripping... as it's running off, right? It's not sitting
in the water. The water, it's being roasted and the water is
running off. So as long as you're dealing with like running off
water, לא מחמיץ, lo machmitz, it doesn't have a chance to become
חמץ. chametz. I should say interestingly
that we have a somewhat of a parallel in discussions about כשר
kashring meat, okay? That
like you know a concern about כשר kashring pieces of meat together,
you put salt on it, now you have to put it on
an incline. By the way, if anybody ever looked at those boxes
of Morton's Kosher salt,
you know, kosher means כשר kashring salt which is why you know
it's like flat and wide or whatever. So anyway, some of those
boxes on the side of it have instructions for כשר kashring meat.
I kid you not, even till today. You can go and look
in the supermarket and they're actually pretty accurate. So anyway, the way
you כשר kashr meat is you put stuff on an incline, so
the blood runs off and it doesn't sit in the blood that's
coming off. But the question is, but the blood is flowing as
long as you do more than one piece of meat, it flows,
right, some is higher and some is lower, it flows from the
top piece and hits the bottom piece. And it still flows there.
So that's the point. Even though it hits it, as long as
it's flowing and it's flowing away, we don't assume it absorbs. So
אביי Abaye is saying something very similar here. I don't buy this
מי פירות mei peiros argument, but as long as it's flowing away,
I will say that it won't actually absorb it to become חמץ.
chametz. דאמר אביי, De'amar Abaye,
now how do we know אביי Abaye reversed himself? Because אביי Abaye
said, האי חצבא דאבישנא, Hai chatzva de'avishna,
a pot that is used for basically roasting grain.
שחיפה Sechifa שרי, shari, if it's upside down and you put it
in the oven, it's okay because I don't get the exact configuration,
there must have whatever, but anyway, somehow then it roasts and the
water that then comes off, you know, runs out of the pot.
I mean it can't be totally a pot upside down because then
it would get trapped at the bottom regardless, but however it's maybe
it's on a grate or something. Anyway, so if the pot is
upside down then the stuff that's in it that's roasted, the water
runs out. That's okay. זקיפה Zekifa אסור, assur, right side up, it's
forbidden because the water will collect at the bottom that comes out
of the grain and that'll be forbidden. So anyway, ורבא אמר אפילו
זקיפה נמי שרי, ve'Rava amar afilu zekifa nami shari, even if it's
done right side up, it's okay even though there's water collecting at
the bottom, מי פירות נינהו, mei peiros ninhu, the water that comes
off of the grain is מי פירות, mei peiros, is fruit water,
מי פירות אין מחמיצין mei peiros ein machmitzin and won't become a
חמץ. chametz. But since אביי Abaye does say that upside down is
okay, why is upside down okay? You got a lot of kernels
of wheat, the stuff at the top is dripping on the stuff
at the bottom, so you see as long as it's running off
it is not a problem.
So what does it mean he changed his mind? He forgot his
own teaching?
Yeah, or he reconsidered. What, people aren't allowed to change their mind?
I mean maybe because of רבא Rava's challenge of how can you
even do one head of wheat, right? So אביי Abaye was, you
know, so and presumably, now you could say okay it's אסור assur
to do even one head of wheat, but presumably you know he
might have been dealing with a reality that nobody's ever questioned, you
know, that we can roast wheat at a to a certain degree.
So whatever it was, it seems that רבא Rava challenged him and
said if you can't do two heads you can't do one head,
and that made him reconsider, but not for the reason that רבא
Rava said. He reconsidered because of this of this idea.
But we learned yesterday that
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said,
חימצו נחלת חוח דלף כל היום כולו, chimtzu necholat hachol delet kol
hayom kulo, you know, but they חמץ, chametz, they didn't disagree with
him before.
No, that's different. That's because a dripping is constantly like, you know,
sort of irritating it as it were. This is a flow.
We wouldn't say, but the flow's still dripping into it.
Yeah, it's not the same. It's not a it's not like an
irritating thing. We wouldn't say if you had flour and you had
it under a faucet, you know, and you had like you had
like you had like you had like some flowing body of water
that it wouldn't become חמץ, chametz, right? We're talking about like a
very type like of a drip that irritates as it were, that
constantly is sort of creating a disturbance. Okay, this is not the
same. This is a flow. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu rabbanan. So rabbis
taught, אין לותתין שעורים בפסח. Ein losesim seorim be'Pesach. You cannot do
לתיתה. lesisa. לתיתה Lesisa is again where you put some water on
the shell of the kernel and you use it to sort of
rub off, you know, maybe with rubbing with your fingers or whatever
to rub off the husk, that whatever the shell, and remove the
bran, not the shell, whatever, anyway, it's a way of removing the
bran and creating just, you know, the the
what's the grain called without the bran? Anyway, the branless kernel. So
anyway, so that's what you would do. It's a way of making
fine flour. So you can't do this
with barley on פסח. Pesach. ואם לתת, Ve'im lasas, if you did,
right, because water it's coming in contact, so how about a חמץ
chametz concern? Now, one thing you have to know which I've not
said explicitly until now but I should have is that we say,
what defines חמץ? chametz? חמץ Chametz is from the time the flour
comes in contact with the water, if you don't get it baked
within 18 minutes or whatever, then it's חמץ. chametz. That's because we
have to quantify everything, okay? And it's based on a גמרא Gemara
from which we get that 18 minute thing. But in the גמרא,
Gemara, you know, we've already seen that there are it's not so
quantifiable, you know, as Michael points out if you have a constant
dripping and an irritation, if you're constantly working working it, even if
you left it alone and you come back and, you know, I
don't know how much time has passed, is it חמץ chametz or
not? The גמרא Gemara speaks about visible signs of what does the
dough look like to indicate whether or not it's fermented. So it's
not such a quantifiable issue. And therefore the גמרא Gemara deals with
the possibility that you could put this kernel of grain. By the
way, also realize that it's a kernel of grain, a kernel of
wheat, of barley, it doesn't necessarily mean that the water gets through.
The idea of the water coming in contact and beginning to have
the chemical process could be very different when we're talking about the
kernel of wheat or barley as opposed to actual flour. Okay, for
example, this issue that אביי Abaye said when I responded to Michael,
that if the water is, you know, is flowing, it doesn't make
the wheat a problem, the kernels of wheat a problem. Would he
say the same if it was flour? Presumably not, right? So there
are different realities about what creates חמץ. chametz. So here he's saying
you don't use the
water to remove the bran of the barley, but even if you
did, it's not necessarily a problem and here's how you'll determine whether
or not it's a problem. We'll talk about wheat in a minute.
ואם לתת, Veim latat, if you did do this, then נתבקעו אסורות.
nitbaku asurot. If you see that the kernel has cracked, which means
the water got into it and then caused it to expand and
it cracked,
so אסורות, asurot, it's forbidden, because then the water did get into
it and it's a חמץ chametz problem. לא נתבקעו, Lo nitbaku, if
it hasn't cracked, מותרות. mutarot. It's permissible because then either no water
got into it or certainly not enough to be a problem, to
have a real effect on the kernel. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose
omer,
שורן בחומץ וחומץ צמתן. shoran bechometz vechometz tzamtan. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says, I have another solution. Even if, what you can do is,
even if you see that they are beginning to, like, expand, it's
not exactly clear if he's saying that even after they've cracked. רש״י
Rashi says, but it sounds like he might even be referring to
that. He says, just throw them into vinegar, and the vinegar will
cause them to, like, you know, right, like shrivel. You know, it
means that it'll impede the fermenting process. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says, that's what I would tell you to do and that'll solve
the problem. Again, whether it's even after it's cracked, it's not clear,
but again, talking about, you know, very practical solutions, it's not all
black and white, there are ways that you can indicate and there
are ways you might even be able to interrupt the fermenting process.
Would אביי Abaye disagree with this though?
Not clear.
If they נתבקעו, nitbaku, you know, he would think he'd say it's
a problem, right? נתבקעו? Nitbaku?
You mean because אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye talks about the water without,
without the measuring of the נתבקעו nitbaku issue. Yeah, that's a very
good, that's a very good point. Although אביי Abaye might have been
talking about the fact that the kernels were already, you know, was
he talking about kernels that were already free from their, from the
bran? So maybe they were more exposed whereas this was, I don't
know enough of the מציאות metziut to respond, but it's a good
question. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel says, אין הלכה כרבי
יוסי. ein halacha kerabbi yose. We don't rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, you can't rely on the vinegar to impede the process. And
presumably רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is only saying it at the grain
level, he wouldn't say it at the flour level. אמר רב חסדא
אמר מר עוקבא, Amar Rav Chisda amar Mar Ukva, לא נתבקעו ממש.
lo nitbaku mamash.
Now we're going to continue to be מחמיר. machmir. First we reject
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, then we say even when it says it's
cracked it's a problem, we don't mean that it literally cracked. אלא
כל שאילו מניחם על פי חבית והן נתבקעו מאליהן. Ella kol she-ilu
menicham al pi chavit ve-hein nitbaku me-aleihen.
Anything that were you to put them על פי חבית al pi
chavit on the top of a barrel, רש״י Rashi assumes a wine
barrel, and somehow the fumes of the wine would interact with the
actual kernels of wheat and that would then lead them to crack,
then it's a problem even if they haven't cracked yet. תוספות Tosfot
has a different גרסא, girsa, not על פי חבית, al pi chavit,
תוספות Tosfot גרסא girsa על פי אבוב, al pi avuv, which is
a type of a like a tube, a metal tube used for
roasting wheat. Okay, so תוספות Tosfot says it's basically, which makes a
little more sense. If you were to apply heat to them they
would crack, then they've already absorbed too much water and it's a
problem. So even at an earlier stage is this going to be
a problem. ושמואל אמר, VeShmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says no, נתבקעו ממש.
nitbaku mamash. It's only a problem if they literally begin to crack.
אבוה דשמואל עבד עובדא בדורא דבי בר חשוש, Avuh d'Shmuel avad uvda
b'dora d'bei bar chashush, שמואל Shmuel actually gave a ruling in the
village of this person בר חשוש, Bar Chashush, נתבקעו ממש nitbaku mamash
on the assumption that they were not a problem until they had
literally cracked. So they had done this, they had actually, you know,
used water to remove the bran from the barley and he said
look, it's okay, they haven't cracked yet, and he wasn't concerned about
maybe they would crack. He said as long as they haven't literally
cracked, it's not a problem.
His father's name was Suspicion?
I don't know, okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said
בעל נפש, baal nefesh, and this is interesting when the גמרא Gemara
refers to this category, a בעל נפש, baal nefesh, somebody who is
concerned for their soul, but no, that's a little heavy-handed. What it
basically means is somebody who, you know, wants to strive for, you
know, greater sort of religious heights or stringencies,
punctilious maybe. רש״י Rashi translates בעל נפש baal nefesh as חסיד, chasid,
and some have the גרסא girsa in רש״י, Rashi, look at... ירא
שמים החרד על נפשו. yarei shamayim hachared al nafsho. So talk about
חרדים, Chareidim, right? And that's fearful for your soul. So somebody who
wants to be basically פרום. frum. If you want to be פרום,
frum, I think with all of the various connotations, well, okay, I
don't know. Anyway, if you want to be extra פרום, frum, לא
ילסוס, lo yilsos, you should not do this. You should not remove
the bran with the water. מאי איריא בעל נפש? mai irya ba'al
nefesh? The גמרא Gemara says, why? What are you talking about somebody
who wants to be פרום? frum? אפילו כולי עלמא נמי? afilu kulei
alma nami? No, even everybody is not allowed to do it. We
just got through
saying דהתניא אין לוסתים שעורין בפסח, dehatanya ein lostim se'orin be'Pesach, you're
not allowed to do it. Now it's true we said בדיעבד, bedi'avad,
there it might be okay based on the circumstances, but certainly to
a no, you're not supposed to. That's a nobody is supposed to
do it. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what רבא Rava means.
בעל נפש אפילו חטים, ba'al nefesh afilu chitin, now this is what
Michael says. If you really want to be פרום, frum, you won't
limit yourself to barley, you'll apply this rule even to wheat, אפילו
חטים דשרירי, afilu chitin deshiri, that are hard, לא ילסוס, lo yilsos,
you shouldn't do it because meaning we only mentioned barley, presumably it's
not so much of a problem wheat, presumably has a
harder sort of shell and the water won't get in so much,
so wheat technically you're allowed, but רבא Rava says if you want
to be פרום, frum, you won't do it even by wheat. אמר
ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said, מאן דציית ליה לאבא, man detzayis lei l'Abba, whoever listens to
אבא, Abba, literally father, but רבא Rava wasn't his father but it
was a respectful way of referring to רבא. Rava. Anybody who listens
to him, אכל נהמא דאיפושא, achal nahama d'ipusha, will wind up eating
spoiled bread. Meaning you're going to have to, נעבעך, nebech, eat whole
wheat bread on
פסח, Pesach, okay, because if you take him seriously, that if you
want to be פרום frum you won't do this process of removing
the bran, then nobody ever gets to eat white flour מצה, matzah,
everybody has to eat whole wheat מצה, matzah, which for them was
a real step down. You'll have to eat spoiled bread on פסח.
Pesach. דהא בי רב הונא לוסתי, deha bei Rav Huna lostei, and
I'll even show you that people didn't bother with that, the people
of the members of the house of רב הונא, Rav Huna, they
would do this לסיסה, lsisah, they would remove the bran from their
wheat. ובי רבא בר אבין לוסתי, u'bei Rava bar Avin lostei, and
the people of the house of רבא בר אבין Rava bar Avin
would do this. Okay, so therefore if you listen to, I'm sorry,
who was this? It wasn't רבא, Rava, it was who was it
who said this? רבה. Rabbah. If you listen to רבה, Rabbah, you're
stuck with eating, נעבעך, nebech, whole wheat מצה matzah on פסח Pesach
and therefore you don't have to worry about it at all, it's
okay with wheat. ורבא אמר, u'Rava amar, now רבא Rava says, אסור
ללוסוס, assur lilsos, רבא Rava went one step further than רבה, Rabbah,
not only is it a good חומרא, chumra, he says it's actually
forbidden. Okay, אלא הכא דתניא, ella hacha de'tanya, according to him what
about the fact that the ברייתא braisa says אין לוסתים שעורין בפסח?
ein lostim se'orin be'Pesach? It says don't do it with the barley.
It's one thing to say if you want to be פרום frum
don't do it with wheat, but how can you say it's forbidden
with wheat? Then why did the ברייתא braisa mention barley? So שעורין
הוא דלא, se'orin hu d'lo,
the ברייתא braisa only forbids barley. הא חטי שרי, ha chiti shari,
wheat is permissible? So the גמרא Gemara says no, according to רבא,
Rava, רבא Rava would say the following: לא מבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya
ka'amar, it goes without saying, meaning it's obvious you can't do wheat.
לא מבעיא חטים, lo mibaya chitin, it goes without saying you can't
do this with wheat, דאית בהו ציריא, de'is behu tzirya, true we
said wheat was harder, but also wheat has more cracks in the
kernels. So איידי בהו מיא, aidi behu maya, we have to be
concerned that the water will go in. אבל שעוריא, aval se'orei, but
barley although it's maybe a little bit less of a little more
porous of a shell, but nevertheless it's a little softer, but nevertheless
דשיעי, deshiei, it's smooth. So אימא שפיר דמי, eima shapir dami, maybe
that would be okay. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that you
can't. So רבא Rava actually says it is forbidden to have to
remove
the bran, to do this לסיסה lsisah from even from wheat. So
according to רבא Rava you would have no way to have white
bread מצה matzah on פסח. Pesach. Fine flour מצה. matzah.
So a linguistic question. שריר sharir here means hard? Yes. So is
that the same לשון lashon as in a כתובה?
ketubah? שריר וקיים, sharir ve'kayam, which is hard and fast? Exactly. Yes,
yes. Um, yes, Charlie.
One of the reasons that grain is washed or soaked is to
remove things like insects. Ah.
So goes back to Dov's point. Maybe they were clearly they weren't
concerned about that.
Yeah. Okay. קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. So הדר אמר רבא,
hadar amar Rava, then רבא Rava said after being so מחמיר machmir
that you can't do it at all with wheat, מותר ללוסוס, mutar
lilsos, actually I find I take it back, you're allowed to. דתניא,
de'tanya, I realized I made a mistake, so it's a day for
people to reverse themselves. How do I know you're allowed to? 'Cause
the ברייתא braisa says יוצאין בפת נקייה
והדראה,
yotzin be'pas nekiya
ve'hadra'ah, you can fulfill your obligation with מצה matzah whether it is
fine flour or whole wheat flour. רש"י Rashi would even say bran.
So and the point there was to say it's not a לחם
עוני lechem oni problem. But forget לחם עוני. lechem oni. How did
you get fine flour for your מצה? matzah? ואי אפשר לנקייה בלא
לסיסה. v'ee efshar nekiya belo lsisah. There's no way to get it.
You did it before פסח. Pesach. Doesn't matter. So it still became
חמץ. chametz. It's not a question of like a תערובת. ta'aroves. It's
a question of חמץ. chametz.
So, but this is soaking to get the הוסה hussa off, right?
Why can't you just get them off without soaking it and
then just Presumably you wouldn't do a good job. Okay, so it's
impossible to get fine flour without doing this לשיסה. leshisa. So clearly
it's allowed. איתיביה רב פפא לרבא, Eisiviah Rav Pappa leRava, so רב
פפא Rav Pappa challenged רבא, Rava, הקמחים והסלתות של נכרים, Hakamchim vehasaltos
shel nochrim,
I will prove to you that you can have סולת soles without
לשיסה, leshisa, without water. Maybe what Michael said, do it dry. Maybe
it is possible. How do we know it? We have a ברייתא
braisa that says you can fulfill your מצה matzah obligation—I'm sorry, הקמחים
והסלתות של נכרים, hakamchim vehasaltos shel nochrim, if you have flour or
whether קמח, kemach, normal flour, or even fine flour from non-Jews, שכפרים
טהורים, shekefarim tehorim, if it is from the villages, it's טהור, tahor,
it's not susceptible for becoming טמא, tamei, ושכרכים, veshekrakim, if you bought
this flour in the cities, then טמאים, tme'im, it's susceptible. So forget
פסח, Pesach, it's a question about whether it's susceptible for becoming טמא.
tamei. What do we know you need to—food to come in contact
with to be susceptible? Water or liquid. So he's saying when they
sell fine flour in the villages, they did it without the use
of water and therefore it's not susceptible. When they sell it in
the cities, where there are higher standards, they did use water. So
you know what? Yes, it's true. You won't get a hundred percent
completely free of any types of, you know, whatever impurities without water,
but you can still do it without water and it could be
called סולת. soles.
But they bought flour from Gentiles to make מצה? matzah?
Well, we're not yet talking about מצה. matzah. This is just טומאה
וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. We'll get to the מצה matzah case in a
second. Okay, but hold on. So we're just proving that you can
have fine flour without the use of water. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama,
what's the reason? משום דלא לשיסי, Mishum delo leshisi, you see they
don't do לשיסה, leshisa, which is a process with water, but nevertheless
they remove the bran, וקרי לה סולת, veka'arei lah soles, and you
still can be able to produce fine flour. So don't tell me
just because you can have a fine flour מצה, matzah, it proves
you're allowed to do this process with water. So the גמרא Gemara
says, it seems to be an excellent proof. So the גמרא Gemara
says, תרגומה קמחא. Targumah kemcha. No, when it says that you can
buy it from the villages, it means the non-fine flour. But the
fine flour, you can
only—you always have to assume came in contact with water. Of course
that's such a—what?
I know, it says both. I mean, what does that mean? It
says you can buy—if you buy it in the villages, it's not,
and if you buy it in the cities, it is. So if
it's only true about the קמח kemach and not the whatever, so
maybe what it means is it told you the סולת soles to
tell you that was a problem in the cities. But I don't
know, it's a very strange answer. Okay, it seemed to have been
a good proof.
Yes, but I once taught on a faculty where there was an
agronomist on the natural sciences faculty. He gave me an article that
described the process by which fine white flour in America today
is
refined
after it's ground, or at some point in the grinding process, it
is sprayed with a very fine mist of water
and
then dried slowly in a warmed environment. He gave it to
me to suggest that all unbaked, unused fine flour in America today
is a חמץ chametz problem. It's so reflective of this entire process.
Fascinating, fascinating.
Although that just says—right—although I'm
not so sure we'd have to check that out, because that sounds
like after the water was applied, after it became flour. Here the
assumption is it's only applied while it's grains. Right, it's different. But
the use of water to actually refine it. Right, exactly. So anyway,
so רבא Rava says, look, רבא Rava resists this proof, which seems
a pretty good proof, and he still says the fact that you
can use fine flour to me says that you can do it
with water.
I don't know. בתר דנפיק, Basar denafik, so anyway, that was the
answer רבא Rava gave whoever it was,
רב פפא. Rav Pappa. And after רבא Rava left, אמר רב פפא
Amar Rav Pappa said, you know, I shouldn't have accepted that answer.
And I in anyway had a good follow-up question. מאי טעמא לא
אימא ליה, Mai ta'ama lo eima lei, I could have proven to
him from
the following—the idea that you can use water in the—that you can
do the process of fine flour without water. I can prove it
to him from the following. מהא דאמר רב זירא אמר רב ירמיה
אמר שמואל, Meha de'amar Rav Zeira amar Rav Yirmiyah amar Shmuel, the
same in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, חטים של מנחות, Chitim shel
menachos,
the wheat that you use for a מנחה, mincha, and a מנחה
mincha remember, you cannot make חמץ. chametz. The wheat you use for
a מנחה, mincha, אין לשיסין אותן, ein leshisin osan,
and therefore he said don't do לשיסה leshisa because we discussed this
earlier, because you don't want it to become חמץ. chametz. Okay, so
you're going to use your wheat for your מנחה mincha without doing
לשיסה. leshisa. But you know what the תורה Torah says has to
be the nature of the flour you use for מנחה? mincha? סולת.
Soles. וקרי להו סולת, Veka'arei lehu soles, and the תורה Torah demands
that it be סולת. soles. So רבא Rava is trying to prove
that the ability to use fine flour shows you're allowed to do
לשיסה. leshisa. He says it's clearly not that. I mean, you might
say that's the הלכה halacha that you're allowed to do לשיסה. leshisa.
but you can't prove it from the use of fine flour.
You can get fine flour and סולת solet without the use of
water. Okay. So anyway so רבא Rava might not have a proof
but at least he's he has reversed himself and said you are
allowed to do לסיסה. lesisa. הדר אמר רבא. Hadar amar Rava. So
רבא Rava went from saying it's totally אסור assur to it's מותר
mutar and then he comes and reverses himself a second time and
says מצוה ללסוס. mitzvah lelisos. It's a מצוה mitzvah to actually remove
the bran and use water. Why? You might just say oh to
get like I don't know nice מצה matzah for פסח? Pesach? No
for a different an ironic reason almost. שנאמר Shene'emar the פסוק pasuk
says
ושמרתם את המצות. Ushmartem es hamatzos. You should guard watch the מצה
matzah which we say watch them to make sure they don't become
חמץ. chametz. אילו דבעי לסיסה Ilo deba'i lesisa if it were not
that you started using water when it was at the earlier stage
when it was you know the grain and removing the bran
שימור למאי? Shimur lemai? What are you watching? What do you have
to watch them to protect that they don't become חמץ? chametz? Now
that seems to be a funny argument. What are you talking about?
When you add the water to the flour. So let's see what
he says. אי שימור דלישה Ei shimur delisha if you mean what
obviously everybody would think that when you add the water to the
flour is when you have to start watching to prevent חמץ chametz
שימור דלישה לאו שימור היא. Shimur delisha lav shimur hi. That is
not a watching meaning maybe that is not necessary. What does it
mean that's not necessary? Let's take a look. Hold on I'm sorry
what? Previous too late? Well let's see meaning or maybe there's other
ways of determining at that stage that it's not חמץ. chametz. Let's
take I don't know what's happening here the camera I'm sorry the
camera started acting funny. Okay. שימור דלישה לאו שימור היא. Shimur delisha
lav shimur hi. Why not?
דאמר רב הונא D'amar Rav Huna because רב הונא Rav Huna says
בציקות של נכרים אדם ממלא כריסו מהן. Betziikos shel nochrim adam memalei
kriso mehen. So here's your case Dov. Too many doves here anyway.
Dough made by non-Jews. You go to a non-Jew and you basically
say I need to make מצות matzos for פסח. Pesach. Do you
have any dough available? Not flour dough. Okay. So you can take
dough made by non-Jews and actually bake מצות matzos out of them.
Now how do you know they didn't become חמץ? chametz? So as
I told you before you a visual inspection. You look at the
dough you see that it's not started to expand you see there
are no cracks in it and based on a visual
inspection you see ah it's not חמץ chametz and therefore you buy
it as dough from the non-Jew. Okay. בציקות Betziikos and you can
fill your stomach with them you eat as much as you want
on פסח Pesach ובלבד שיאכל כזית מצה באחרונה. Uvilvad she'yochal kezayis matzah
b'achronah. But in order to do the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah
it's interesting here the גמרא Gemara assumes that the מצוה mitzvah of
מצה matzah comes at the end of the סדר Seder you have
to make sure that you have מצה matzah that was actually watched
by Jews even earlier on even from the time
of kneading.
Is that a חמץ chametz problem or is that a כוונה kavana
problem?
No it's a כוונה kavana problem. Well לשמה lishmah right. I'll get
I'll answer that in more detail minute but it's obviously not a
חמץ chametz concern because you're allowed to eat the other stuff on
פסח. Pesach. Right. So number one you see an amazing thing that
you could buy dough and make a visual inspection and determine it's
not
חמץ. chametz. But רבא Rava says okay so you certainly don't need
שימור shimur even at the kneading stage even at the in order
that it not be חמץ. chametz. How about שימור shimur in order
to fulfill your obligation of מצה? matzah? When does that have to
kick in? So it's clear that it can't begin at it that
it has to be prior to it becoming dough. So רבא Rava
says so let's take a look. באחרונה אין B'achronah in you see
it's only a problem at the end.
בראשונה לא. Berishonah lo. But you can't use these earlier doughs for
you know for מצה. matzah. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
משום דלא עביד בהו שימור Mishum delo avid behu shimur
because you didn't do שימור shimur so it's not חמץ chametz based
on visual
inspection but it hasn't had the שימור shimur and can't be used
for the מצוה. mitzvah. So he says so why's that a problem?
וליעבד ליה שימור מאפיה ואילך. V'li'avad lei shimur me'afiyah va'eilach. Why not
do the שימור shimur starting from the time you bought the dough
from the time of baking? אלא לאו שמע מינה Ella lav shema
mina we see שימור מעיקרא בעינן Shimur me'ikara ba'inan that it's not
enough to have some type of a שימור shimur you need שימור
shimur from the very get-go. Meaning his argument is the following. Not
in order to not to become חמץ chametz as we see you
can do a visual inspection but in order to fulfill the מצוה
mitzvah of מצה matzah you need a שימור shimur that goes beyond
just knowing it's not חמץ. chametz. You need a שימור shimur to
observe that it has not had that problem. So he says and
just a שימור shimur at some stage in the process isn't enough.
To do it at the אפיה afiyah that's too late. It needs
to be at the earliest stage. So רבא's Rava argument is so
why should the earliest stage be defined as when you add the
water to the flour? Since it has the potential of becoming חמץ
chametz earlier when you did the bran removal which also had water
so you see that you need to do it at the beginning
of the process. Middle of the process doesn't work. So if baking
isn't enough then kneading isn't enough. It should have to go from
the very earliest stage. of the process from when the water hit
the bran, hit the kernel.
So what is this food? It's not מצה. matzah.
It's מצה, matzah, it's just not מצת מצוה. matzas mitzvah. It's like
מצה עשירה. matzah ashira. It's מצה matzah that
doesn't have the לשמה lishma requirement, but it's totally מצה. matzah. You
make המוציא, hamotzi, you just can't use it for the מצוה mitzvah
of the סדר seder night. Now I do want to say the
reason it says at the end, does that mean... there's a whole
debate in the ראשונים Rishonim nowadays. We make the ברכה bracha of
על אכילת מצה al achilas matzah at the first כזית kezayis of
מצה. matzah. Then we have the אפיקומן. afikomen. Though some ראשונים Rishonim
say, we'll discuss this more in the tenth פרק, perek, that the
אפיקומן afikomen is the real מצוה mitzvah of מצה, matzah, not the
one we eat at the beginning. So you might get support from
the idea that here it says that you eat the מצה matzah
of מצוה mitzvah at the end. רש"י Rashi however says we could
be talking about the time when there's a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach.
And when there's a קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, the מצה matzah of
the מצוה mitzvah is eaten with the קרבן פסח korban Pesach and
the קרבן פסח korban Pesach is eaten at the end. It's eaten
על השובע. al hasova. Okay?
So how do you get there from it's a מצוה mitzvah to
do לתיתה? letita? I didn't get the jump there.
It's not a מצוה mitzvah to do... you said that. מצוה... mitzvah...
oh because so... oh you mean that's a good point, meaning you
could say if you do לתיתה, letita, then you have to do
שמירה shemira at the beginning. Right. But it doesn't mean you have
to create the scenario that requires it. You create your own problem.
That is true. That is... well let's see even how the גמרא
Gemara responds. The גמרא Gemara responds in a similar way. So
the
גמרא Gemara says ומי מאי umi mai says who? דילמא שאני התם,
dilma shani hasam, maybe there it's different. To דבעידנא דנחית לשימור, de-be-idna
de-nachis l'shimu, there from the moment that שימור shimur became relevant when
water hit the flour, לא עביד ליה שימור. lo avid leih shimur.
You didn't do it. אבל היכא דבעידנא דנחית לשימור עביד ליה שימור,
aval heicha de-be-idna de-nachis l'shimu avid leih shimur, as long as you
started your שימור shimur when it became relevant, when the water hit
it, הכי נמי דשימור דלישה הוי שימור. hachi nami de-shimur de-leisha havei
shimur. Maybe that's sufficient, meaning exactly that. If you used water earlier
and did לתיתה, letita, you have to do שימור shimur earlier. Okay,
but that doesn't prove that you're required to start the process, you
know, to add the water earlier. Maybe the הלכה halacha is you
have to do שימור shimur from the beginning of when the water
was added, whenever that stage might be. Very reasonable position and there's
no מצוה mitzvah to do this לתיתה letita in order to get
to שימור shimur to be at the very beginning of the process.
But you see where we're going here. We're going to... it's a
little ironic. On the one hand he's מיקל, meikel, he allows you
and even requires you to use water to remove the bran. On
the other hand, it becomes a חומרא chumra on this concept of
you know of שימור לשם מצה. shimur l'shem matzah. Okay.
Well maybe it doesn't mean it's a מצוה mitzvah to do לתיתה,
letita, it means that that means in order that the product be
the מצה של מצוה matzah shel mitzvah you have to do לתיתה.
letita.
Yeah, but even that the גמרא Gemara says is right. We're talking
about for מצה matzah of מצוה. mitzvah. That's clear. When he's saying
a מצוה mitzvah he doesn't mean for other מצה, matzah, he means
for the מצה matzah of מצוה. mitzvah. But even that the גמרא
Gemara says is not clear because why not just say whenever you
start whenever you add the water, that's when the מצוה mitzvah of
שימור shimur starts, not that you have to add the water early.
Okay? But yes, we're not talking about general, we're talking specifically now
about מצה matzah of מצוה. mitzvah. ואפילו הכי, va'afilu hachi, even though
once again a good argument was made against רבא, Rava, you know,
not to disprove him, but at least to challenge at least to
say that he didn't have evidence, he didn't have a proof. Even
though that's true, לא הדר ביה lo hadar beih רבא, Rava, he
didn't reverse himself. Like any good person of a firm conviction that
it doesn't matter what the evidence is, I know right, you know.
He changed his mind three times. Exhausted.
That could be too. Okay, לא הדר ביה. lo hadar beih. דאמר
להו להנו דמהפכי כיפי, de-amar lehu l'hanu de-mahepkhei kifi, he said to
those that would turn over the bundles of wheat, meaning you know
they're there in the fields and they're making the bundles of wheat,
כי מהפכיתו הפיכו לשם מצוה. ki mahephkhei hapeikhu l'shem mitzvah.
When you are binding up these bundles, do it for מצה matzah
of מצוה. mitzvah. Even without any water. So he really developed this
idea that שימור shimur has to begin way at the beginning. Of
course if that's true, then there's again it's no proof that you
use water for the לתיתה. letita. Maybe there's just a מצוה mitzvah
of שימור shimur even before you've used water because now he's telling
them do שימור shimur when you're making the bundles.
Is this a כוונה kavana issue and not a שימור shimur issue?
Right, sounds to be. I'm going to get back to that. Let
me just finish this point. אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar, wait a minute,
שימור מעיקרא מתחילתו ועד סופו בעינן. shimur meikara mit'chilato v'ad sofo ba'inan.
You see you need שימור shimur from the very beginning. And if
you look at the sides... right, and if you look even he
went even further, even without water. And if you look at the
sides, meaning to be maybe make sure that no water, you know,
be just שימור shimur that maybe water will come in contact, went
from שימור shimur of when water comes in contact make sure it
doesn't become חמץ chametz to a שימור shimur of make sure no
water comes in contact with it. Um right, you understand that shift,
right? Anyway if you look at the side of your box of
שמורה shmura matzahs, it says שמורה מצה shmura matzah by the way
is where we get that from, and it says שמור משעת קצירה.
shamur mishat ktzira. Okay? Which is basically following this position of רבא.
Rava. Okay. מר בריה דרבינא, Mar breih de-Ravina, and now to end
the story, מר Mar the son of רבינא. Ravina. מנקטלי אימיה בערבי,
mankatlei imei b'arvi, his mother would go ahead and
collect sheaves of stalks of wheat and put them in a, you
know, and put them in a, and put them in like a
type of a, what, kneading trough, like in a container and basically
save them and hold on to them until it was time to
make them into מצה. matza. So basically, you know, his mother would
go ahead and do this and watch the wheat and protect it
for him from the very beginning of the cutting. Now, how do
we, so women, right, so women were doing it too. Now, how
do we rule about this? So first of all, I want to
address the issue that Dov has been raising, which is an important
question, which is, what is the idea of שימור? shimur? And this
has relevance beyond just this question, it also has relevance to the
machine מצה matza issue. Is שימור shimur because we saw before the
idea of כוונה, kavana, if you remember, that if you're watching it
in order to prevent it from חמץ chametz in order to use
it for רקיקי נזיר, rakikei nazir, that could be a problem, even
though you're still watching to prevent it from חמץ. chametz. So is
here the שימור shimur like, I am watching this לשם מצת מצוה,
l'shem matzas mitzva, you know, when you go to the bakeries in
Boro Park or whatever before they start kneading, they all say לשם
מצת מצוה, l'shem matzas mitzva, right, so it's like לשמה. lishma. Is
that what it is? Or it doesn't mean that you're having, you
know, you have to have in mind that I'm going to make
this into the מצה matza of the מצוה, mitzva, but what it
does mean is you have to watch it and make sure it
doesn't become חמץ. chametz. Okay, now what's the difference? So well, besides
whether what are you thinking in your head, the difference is this
is an issue that came up with machine מצה matza and using
it for the מצת מצוה matzas mitzva because if it's just an
issue of not defining it as לשמה lishma because that's in your
head and that defines the nature of the מצה, matza, if it's
just an issue of watching it from becoming חמץ, chametz, maybe at
a very early stage from the cutting, but still it's an idea
of a process of watching and protecting, not of a לשמה lishma
process, then machine מצה matza shouldn't be an issue. But if it's
a לשמה lishma process, then maybe it doesn't end at the, you
know, at the kneading and whatnot, maybe you need human involvement at
every stage with having in your head לשם מצת מצוה. l'shem matzas
mitzva.
So the guy turning on the switch
can say, I'm doing this לשמה. lishma. Okay, so then the question,
if you turn on the switch and you think about it and
the machine runs for itself by for 10 hours, does that still
work? So anyway, those are some of the issues that come up
with machine מצה matza and is there an idea of לשמה lishma
in addition to the idea of שימור? shimur? That's one question. In
terms of how do we פסקן, pasken, it's a major debate of
the ראשונים. Rishonim. Some ראשונים פסקן Rishonim pasken like the end of
the גמרא, Gemara, you have to do it משעת קצירה. mishas katzira.
Some say no, from the very last story, this was just רבא's
Rava approach. רבא Rava clearly here is being מחמיר machmir and the
last story makes it clear, oh his mom used to do it
for him, like that's a nice little thing but it's a חומרא
chumra and some reject it. And there are some that say that
that, you know, you have to do it but you do it
not so early as from the time when it's cut, not so
late as only when water is added, but you do it from
the moment where there's a serious concern it might come in contact
with water. So הרא"ש the Rosh says, for example, when you grind
the wheat and turn it into flour, not just because now flour's
more susceptible to becoming חמץ, chametz, but also where would they grind
their wheat? Anybody know? In what type of a mill? A water
mill. So you're grinding your wheat in the environment where there's a
lot of water around, that's where it begins. So it's again not
at a, you know, not only when it comes in contact with
water but not at the very beginning but when there's a serious
possibility of water, that's what הרא"ש the Rosh says. But there's a
major debate and again this is an issue not about חמץ chametz
but about using מצה matza for Seder night. Yes, Michael.
What about this לטיטה L'titah then? Is there a consensus of whether
you're allowed to?
I forgot to check. I'm pretty sure so I don't know the
answer. I mean we use fine flour מצה, matza, we don't use
whole wheat מצה, matza, but whether we do it with לטיטה L'titah
or not, yeah that I don't know. I'd have to check.
And the whole thing with ושמרתם את המצות Ushmartem es hamatzos is
it's oh for the rabbis it's made it so complicated because it
doesn't it could mean keep the מצה matza like ושמרתם את יום
השבת. Ushmartem es yom haShabbos. It doesn't mean look at it. It
means to keep the מצוה. mitzva.
Right, to observe the מצוה mitzva of eating מצה. matza.
Right, so ושמרתם את המצות Ushmartem es hamatzos could have meant
right it's like ושמרתם את יום השבת, Ushmartem es yom haShabbos, right,
right like keep this מצוה, mitzva, right, like ושמרו בני ישראל
את השבת,
V'shamru venei Yisrael es
haShabbos, right, right
I understand.
Isn't
it interesting that in English we also say observe which means in
the one hand to look at and in the other hand to
actually do.
Right, so they didn't necessarily have to go this route
of
looking at it, watching it. As with many things, Rivka, as with
many things. Right, it's not פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. So
complicated. Not necessarily what was intended.
That is true.
Okay. All right. So now let's try to see if we can
get to the משנה. Mishna. Okay. ההוא ארבא דחיטי. Hahu arva d'chiti.
So you have a certain trough filled with wheat. With that had
in it wheat kernels, right? We saw before the sheaves were being,
the stalks were being kept in this, in a trough. So, similar
story. A trough that had these wheat kernels in it, ההוא ארבא
דחיטי דטבע בכישתא, Hahu arva d'chiti d'tava b'chishta, that it was submerged
into a river. It fell into a river. Okay? So now obviously
these are problem, I mean it's a serious concern. It's not just
לתיתא latita which is momentary, moment or whatever, and nobody was watching
this. So you have a real concern now that these wheat kernels
are חמץ. chametz. What are you going to do with them? So
שרי רבא לזבוני לנכרים. Sharei Rava l'zabuni l'nochrim. So Rava said fine,
it was before פסח, Pesach, sell it to non-Jews. What do I
care? Sell it to non-Jews. Okay. איתיביה רבא בר ליוואי לרבא, Eiteivei
Rava bar Livai l'Rava, so Rava bar Livai challenged Rava. בגד שעירב
בו כלאיים, Beged she'eirev bo kilayim, if you have a garment that
there's a string of linen in it somewhere and you can't find
it, a wool garment. So there's שעטנז shatnez here, but you don't
know where and you can't remove it. So what do you do?
הרי זה לא ימכרנו לנכרי, Harei zeh lo yimkerenu l'nochri, don't say
I'll just sell it to a non-Jew. ולא יעשה בו מרדעה לחמור,
V'lo ya'aseh bo marda'ah l'chamor, and don't make it like a blanket
for the, a saddle blanket.
Okay, even though, by the way, I should say technically you can
sit on שעטנז shatnez as long as it says בגד כלאיים שעטנז
לא יעלה עליך. beged kilayim shatnez lo ya'aleh alecha. As long as
it's under you and not over you. Normally we say we're afraid
because maybe some strings will cover,
will go on top of you. And for some reason we're not
concerned about that here. But anyway, what maybe you are. But no,
the concern here does not seem to be that. The concern seems
to be that if you sell it to a non-Jew or you
use it as a saddle blanket, you'll forget that there's שעטנז shatnez
because it's not visible and you will come to then wind up
making a garment out of it. I'm sorry, wait.
Why can't sell it to a non-Jew, why?
Because he will go back and sell it to a Jew and
it won't be obvious that it has שעטנז. shatnez.
So even if I'm selling it to some guy in India, I
can't do that?
Well, okay, I think the גמרא Gemara was not dealing with selling
it by eBay and shipping it to China. The גמרא Gemara was
dealing with your local non-Jew, okay? Anyway, maybe the guy in China
will turn around and sell it on eBay and send it back
to a Jew. Okay, so
anyway. Look, nowadays everybody checks for שעטנז shatnez because it's not obvious
for everyone. So anyway, so I don't know. אבל עושין אותו תכריכין
למת, Aval osin oto tachrichin l'meit, you can use it for shrouds
because once you use it for, and right, and you, even if
you changed your mind after you've used it for shrouds, it's אסור
בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. It becomes like the מת meit itself and therefore
it becomes off-limits. Now,
לנכרי מאי טעמא לא? L'nochri mai ta'ama lo? Why can't you sell
it to a non-Jew? לאו משום דהדר מזבין ליה לישראל? Lav mishum
d'hadar mazbin lei l'Yisrael? Because he'll turn around and sell it back
to a Jew. Not necessarily maliciously, he'll just make a profit off
of it. But you won't see. So here too, this guy, you'll
sell him your wheat kernels that are now a serious concern of
חמץ chametz in a non-visible way. Interesting, although before we talked about
cracking and this and that. Anyway, here the גמרא Gemara assumes that
maybe because it was submerged that even if it's not visible it's
a concern. And how can you sell it to a non-Jew? It
might come back into Jewish hands. So הדר אמר רבא, Hadar amar
Rava, so Rava accepted the critique. And Rava's doing a lot of
reversing himself. That's phenomenal, what a paradox. Right, Rava reversed himself and
said fine, לזבנינהו קבא קבא לישראל. L'zabninhu kava kava l'Yisrael. So it
was enough before פסח, Pesach, he said sell them like ounce by
ounce to Jews. Meaning don't sell the whole thing, he won't finish
it in time. But presumably people there didn't leave stuff sitting around
in their pantry. So if you're buying wheat it means within a
few days you're going to turn it into bread. So sell little
little amounts each one to a different person and they'll definitely use
it up before פסח. Pesach. What? To a ישראל.
Yisrael. Right, means even to a ישראל.
Yisrael. Unless you would דווקא davka be, well maybe דווקא davka to
a ישראל Yisrael because they know פסח Pesach is around, you tell
them what, you tell them that it's חמץ. chametz. And they know
פסח Pesach is around the corner. כי היכי דכליה קמי פסחא. Ki
haychi d'kalya kamei Pischa. That way it'll be used up before פסח.
Pesach. By the way, I will just note, I don't want to
discuss it in depth, but תוספות Tosafot discusses this idea of using
שעטנז shatnez for a מת meit about this question
about how, is there an issue of like the גמרא Gemara speaks
about not wearing your ציצית tzitzit out because of
לועג לרש, lo'eg l'rash, mocking the מת meit that the מת meit
can't do מצוות. mitzvot. How does that play out with this idea
of not being concerned that you're putting כלאיים kilayim on a מת?
meit? Isn't that also mocking? תוספות Tosafot says well maybe ציצית tzitzit
is unique and different because
ציצית tzitzit sort of represents all the מצוות. mitzvot. But anyway he
raises the issue. But then it's a very classic, it's a classic
תוספות, Tosafot, it occurs in a number of times in ש"ס, Shas,
that he points out that our process, because the גמרא Gemara says
that you tear the ציצית tzitzit off of the garment.
I'm sorry, no. Our גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, if you
take a look, it says
one minute,
what was it? So תוספות Tosafot says ומה שאנו עושים, u'mah she'anu
osim, nowadays we do. Excuse me, the גמרא Gemara says,
the גמרא Gemara has you have a garment with ציצית tzitzit on
it. Our מנהג minhag is to take the ציצית tzitzit off. And
if you look at תוספות אבל Tosafot aval here, I said I
wasn't going to say it but I couldn't resist. Near the end,
he says... ומה שאנו עושים, u-mah she-anu osim, where were we? I'm
trying to find it.
ומה שמסירין, u-mah she-mesirin, the line starts with the word מסירין. mesirin.
It's about שמסירים she-mesirim about 12, 15 lines before the end. ומה
שמסירין בזמן הזה מטליתות של מתים, u-mah she-mesirin ba-zeman ha-zeh mi-taliyos shel
mesim, how do we remove the ציצית tzitzis from the טליתות talityos
of the dead bodies? If according to the גמרא Gemara you're דוקא
davka it would be a לועג לרש lo'eg larash problem and you
should have the ציצית tzitzis on. So סומכין אהא דתניא במסכת שמחות,
somchin aha de-tanya be-masechet semachot, we rely on מסכת שמחות, masechet semachot,
which has kind of it works but it ultimately was edited by
the גאונים. geonim. אבא שאול בן בטנית ציווה לבניו קברו אותי תחת
מרגלותיו של אבא והתירו תכלת מפאליוני. Abba Shaul ben Batnis tziva le-banav
kivru osi tachas margelosav shel abba ve-hatiru techeles mi-palyoni. So anyway he
said to his sons take תכלת techeles which means ציצית tzitzis off
of my garment. So we rely on a line in מסכת שמחות
masechet semachot even against the גמרא Gemara and we take the ציצית
tzitzis off. So then תוספות Tosfos says ובכמה דברים אנו סומכין על
ספרים חיצוניים ומניחים גמרא שלנו u-vi-chama devarim anu somchin al sefarim chitzoniyim
u-manichim Gemara she-lanu and there are a couple of places that we
rely on non-בבלי Bavli sources, on ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, on
מדרש, Midrash, or whatever, on these מסכתות קטנות masechtos ketanos against the
בבלי. Bavli. And then he gives some other examples dealing with like
what we say at various הפטרות haftaros etc. And by the way
I should mention that scholars will say that some of this has
to do with the fact that תוספות Tosfos in Germany comes from
you know the culture comes from Italy which comes from ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. That the general assumption is that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
Jews like went and the culture went via to Italy and from
there to Germany and France as opposed to the ספרדי Sephardi lands
which came more from בבל Bavel culture and from and from Babylonian
Jews. And therefore we find that sometimes אשכנזי Ashkenazi Jewry has ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael practices in defiance of or contrary to בבל Bavel
practices. So I just interesting that he mentions that. Let's just finish
up to the משנה. Mishnah. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our Rabbis taught:
אין מוללין את הקדירה בפסח, ein molin es ha-kederah be-Pesach,
you cannot מולל mollel which means again add a grain as a
or you know a wheat kernels as a thickener to the to
the pot on פסח Pesach for obvious reasons.
Right. רש"י Rashi says excuse me with flour here not with wheat
not with the kernels. והרוצה שימלול מה יעשה נותן את הקמח ואחר
כך נותן את החומץ. ve-ha-rotzeh she-yimlo mah ya'aseh nosen es ha-kemach ve-achar
kach nosen es ha-chometz.
So again remember the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose we said before that
said that חומץ chometz
prevents it from fermenting. So here the גמרא Gemara says you can
do it put the put the flour in and then add the
חומץ. chometz. Now you might think it's better to have the חומץ
chometz there first so the flour doesn't get a chance to hit
the water without the חומץ. chometz. But the גמרא Gemara assumes it's
better the חומץ chometz later because then the חומץ chometz hits it
when the חומץ chometz is undiluted. Okay.
What's vinegar made out of? What's חומץ? chometz?
What type of vinegar? Like is it wheat vinegar?
I don't know. That's a good question.
I mean it's possible that wheat vinegar is not חמץ chametz correct?
Yeah but do they make vinegar by adding water?
I thought what's that process called?
They distill it? Yeah but isn't it with the addition of water
or not? I don't know.
I forget how you distill things.
Okay anyway. ויש אומרים ve-yesh omrim some say אף נותן את החומץ
ואחר כך נותן את הקמח, af nosen es ha-chometz ve-achar kach nosen
es ha-kemach,
you can start with the חומץ. chometz. מאן יש אומרים, man yesh
omrim, who is this יש אומרים? yesh omrim? אמר רבי חסדא רבי
יהודה היא, amar Rabbi Chisda Rabbi Yehudah hi, it's רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehudah who said who says that even חומץ chometz in a cooking
in a pot has power to it. Where do you see this?
דתנן, de-tenan, taking a proof from a an unexpected source: האילפס והקדירה
שהעבירן מרותחין לא יתן לתוכן תבלין בשבת, ha-ilpas ve-ha-kederah she-he-eviran merosachin lo
yiten le-sochan tavlin be-Shabbos, the sort of the frying pan and the
קדירה kederah that you took them boiling off of the stove top
don't put spices on שבת Shabbos because it'll cook the spices. This
is a כלי ראשון kli rishon that has boiling stuff in it.
Don't put spices in it it'll cook the spices on שבת. Shabbos.
Even though it's off the flame.
Even though it's off the flame. אבל נותן לתוך הקערה או לתוך
התמחוי, aval nosen le-soch ha-kearah o le-soch ha-tamchoi, you can put your
spices into the soup or whatever the stew that's in the קערה
kearah or the תמחוי tamchoi is another type of whatever a dish
a plate or a bowl. Why? Because that's a כלי שני. kli
sheni. So this is the basic principle that כלי ראשון kli rishon
is a problem off the flame כלי שני kli sheni is okay.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehudah omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says לכל
הוא נותן חוץ מדבר שיש בו חומץ וציר le-chol hu nosen chutz
mi-davar she-yesh bo chometz va-tzir except for something that has in it
חומץ chometz or fish brine. And this could be read even לחומרא
le-chumra that if it has this חומץ chometz even in a כלי
שני kli sheni it's a problem. Why? Because the חומץ chometz will
have a effect on the food and allow it to cook. So
presumably and it'll be a בישול. bishul. So presumably again obviously there's
a lot of distinctions you could make between the comparison but רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says that the חומץ chometz still has pungency even
if it's already in the תבשיל. tavshil. Okay. So גמרא Gemara says
וניוקמה כרבי יוסי, ve-neyokmah ke-Rabbi Yose, why not say this idea that
the חומץ chometz in the תבשיל tavshil still has pungency let's say
that's like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. דתניא de-tanya we taught in a
ברייתא braita רבי יוסי אומר שורין בחומץ והחומץ צומתן, Rabbi Yose omer
shorin be-chometz ve-ha-chometz tzomtan, that he he's the one that we said
before when these wheat kernels start cracking just put them into the
חומץ. chometz. So the answer is Yes, that says vinegar works but
not that it works if it's already in the pot. כי אשמעינן
לרבי יוסי ki ashmeinan lerabbi yosi when did Rabbi Yosi say the
vinegar works? הני מילי דאיתא בעיניה hani mili de'isa be'inei that's when
you have it by itself, undiluted vinegar. So put it, throw the
vinegar on it, it'll help. אבל על ידי תערובת aval al yedei
ta'aroves it doesn't mean if you start put the vinegar first in
the pot, then it's already been diluted and it's mixed with other
stuff. לא, lo, maybe that would not do the job. So once
again we get that vinegar can impede the process and the question
is will that help even if it's already been mixed into the
pot? עולא אמר אחד זה ואחד זה אסור. Ulla amar echad ze
ve'echad ze assur. You know what, I don't care whether vinegar first
or vinegar last, don't do this type of stuff. What, you're going
to put flour in your pot on פסח Pesach in your soup?
משום mishum and this reflects obviously a general approach but approach we
are well familiar with with פסח, Pesach, לך לך אמרינן נזירא. lech
lech amrinan nezira. סחור סחור sechor sechor לכרמא לא תקרב. lecharma lo
sikrav. Go away, go away, we say to the נזיר. nazir. Go
around, go around, to the vineyard don't get even close. So a
נזיר nazir is only not allowed to eat grapes or wine but
what do we tell the נזיר? nazir? You don't say walk through
a vineyard. You say take a detour, don't go through the vineyard
which means you got to be keep your distance, be safe, basically
saying like any normal anybody nowadays who would read this גמרא Gemara
would say are you crazy? You think you're going to put flour
in your soup on פסח Pesach and tell me that oh the
vinegar that'll solve the problem? Okay, so clearly that idea is already
beginning in the גמרא. Gemara. Technically לפני עיוור lifnei iver argument
for the נזיר?
nazir? Maybe, but here it's also
self-imposed, we have to protect ourselves from dangerous situations. Okay, so last
story. רב פפי שרי להו לבורדקי דבי ריש גלותא. Rav Pappi shari
lehu lebordakei devei Reish Galusa.
Rav Pappi allowed the cooks in the house of the ריש גלותא
Reish Galusa or the bakers לממחא קדירה בחסיסי lemimcha kedeira bechasisi
to thicken the pot with this like roasted grains is what רש"י
Rashi says that means. תוספות Tosafos says it actually means something else,
I don't know, lentil flour, of course lentil flour shouldn't be חמץ
chametz at all. Anyway, so presumably he felt that if it was
already roasted like we saw at the beginning of today, it wasn't
going to be a problem. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava
said איכא דשרי כי האי מילתא בדוכתא דשכיחי עבדי? ika deshari ki
hai milsa beduchta deshchichi avdei? Is there anybody that would really allow
such a thing when you're dealing with like servants or slaves? Meaning
who can trust them to do a good job? We began today's
דף daf by saying don't thicken your pot or whatever, maybe you
won't roast it well enough. And here he's letting them do it
with people that maybe generally don't do the job certainly well enough
servants? Presumably,
I don't know, not clear. איכא דאמרי ika de'amri some say and
interesting way the גמרא Gemara chooses to end this whole discussion. רבא
גופא מחי לה קדירה בחסיסי. Rava gufa machi leh kedeira bechasisi. Rava
himself did it, he added these grains, this grain as a thickener.
So you go back and forth in the גמרא Gemara between God
forbid you should even think about doing such a thing to saying
no, maybe there are ways you can do it as long as
you're paying attention and making sure you're not getting into trouble. Okay.
מחי Machi I thought מחי machi meant the opposite, to push away.
Yeah,
I mean מחי machi I don't know, here רש"י Rashi says that
it means to thicken a pot. Yeah, I think so. I don't
know enough of the grammar to tell you if it's the same
word or if it's the grammatical construction makes it mean something different.
Thanks to the question, vinegar, it is made from alcohol which can
come from many sources. Yes, it can be made from wheat or
barley.
Yes, but with the addition of water is the question.
Yeah, to distill it.
I imagine you have to add the water. Yes. So if you're
making... no,
the גמרא Gemara very often, I think I should have said at
the time, I think סתם חומץ stam chometz in the גמרא Gemara
is wine vinegar.
Yeah, in the United States it is very rare because it is
generally made from corn
or
apples
because corn is produced in such humongous quantities.
It reminds me... welcome back, where were we? Distillation. Oh right, wait,
weren't you going to bring up... oh that was through the night.
And then it re... how was it? The vapors then turn back
to the liquid form.
It becomes ethyl alcohol.
But what does that explain or re-explain to
me using the tips of your fingertips...
well it is, I mean you're
why do you feel that ethyl alcohol... all you're doing is turning
the liquid into vapor and
then re-cooling it in the tubing very slowly over a period of
time. There's ethyl
alcohol. But does that question make sense?
That's when I forgot what it's made from. It can be made
from
wheat, it can be made from corn.
Maybe next week we can pick it up.
Okay, that'd be good. Like I said, my hand-eye coordination won't necessarily
be better, but my endurance will.
Are you playing racquetball or something?
Yeah, דוב Dov is having רחמנות rachmanus on me and then playing
racquetball with me.
Wait one second, I wanted to ask once about לודג' בראש... Lodge
Brosh... remember it came up in our אגרות קודש Igros Kodesh about
taking off onesies with the לודג' בראש Lodge Brosh because even people
alive don't even do it? Remember that one? I think we had
that in מנחה. Mincha. I forgot how that went.
Yeah, so do I.
But you know what I'm talking about?
I do know, yeah. Exactly. We were saying how you have to
be careful about לשון הרע loshon hara even with people
that are no longer with us. Because it's actually an explicit הלכה
halacha in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. If you look in סימן
תר''ו, Siman Tof-Reish-Vav, the רמ''א Rema says that there's a תקנה takkana
from the קדמונים kadmonim not to speak רע ra about the מתים.
meisim. And it's based on that גמרא Gemara in ברכות, Berachos, I
think it's on דף י''ח, Daf Yud Ches, where they talk about
whether the dead are aware of what's happening. And the מסקנא maskana
is that they are. So that's why if you do it, you
have to go to the קבר kever with a מנין minyan and
ask for מחילה. mechila. It's really interesting. And the משנה ברורה Mishnah
Berurah mentions it right there as something people should be aware of,
especially around אלול Elul when we're all being more careful with our
speech. Definitely.